Guide to the Peter Wellington Alexander Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Arranged Series
  - Manuscripts & Documents
    - Alexander, Theresa Shorter (Mrs. Peter Wellington Alexander) Scrapbook of newspaper clippings. Includes columns about Col. Alexander and Bishop Beckwith, and others in the family. [Augusta, GA] [Sept. 1866 -Nov. 1893?]., 12 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3)
    - Alexander, Theresa Shorter (Mrs. Peter Wellington Alexander) Miscellaneous business papers, including a letter from J. T. Estell on Texas property. [v.p.] 1 June 1871 -28 Feb. 1893., 4 ms.d.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 12)
    - Ferrat, John B. Letterbook. Norfolk and Richmond, VA 9 May 1862 -1 July 1863., a.ms.s., 39 p.; ["Captured from the Yankees at the Battle of Sharpsburg Md. Sept. 17th 1862." in whichPrivate Ferrat has written. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 12)
    - Fillmore, Millard[Untitled]. [n.p.] 10 July 1852, ms.d.s., 1 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3)
    - Van Dorn, Earl Document granting authority to Col. James R. Shaler to raise a Regiment of Partizan Rangers for service in Missouri. Camp Ingraham, Miss. 3 June 1862., a.d.s., 1 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 12)
    - Wayne, Henry L. Special Order No. 126: Proceedings of a Court of Inquiry into imputations against Col. Cary W. Stiles. Milledgeville, GA 19 Sept. 1864., t.d.s., 1 p.; 9 ms.p. encl.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 12)
    - Alexander, Peter Wellington and wife. Photographs. [n.p.] [n.d.], [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3)
  - Copybooks, Letterbooks etc
    Gift of Mrs. Robert P. Hamilton.
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Department of Alabama and West Florida. Copybook of General and Special Orders. Mobile, etc. 14 Oct. 1861 -15 Aug. 1862., ms.vol., 410 p.; 1, 50, 90 p.; [Orders by Generals Beauregard; Bragg; Samuel Cooper; Albert Sidney Johnston; JonesMitchell Withers; et al. Microfilm Reel 94-2007-2.] (Box 7)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Departments of Alexandria, the Potomac, and Mississippi Copybook of Letters and Orders Manassus and Fairfax, VA and Jackson, Tenn. 2 June 1861 -29 April 1862, ms.vol., 452 p.; [Copy of important public letters and orders of General Beauregard's command. Microfilm Reel 94-2007-2.] (Box 7)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Department of Mississippi Copybook of Telegrams [v.p.] 18 Feb. -11 Aug. 1862, ms.vol., 202 p.; [Copy of important public telegrams of General Beauregard's command. Microfilm Reel94-2007-2.] (Box 7)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Department of Mississippi Copybook of Letters and Orders Corinth and Tupelo, Miss., and Chattanooga, Tenn. 29 April -6 Sept. 1862, ms.vol., 208 p.; [Copy of letters, Special and General Orders of General Beauregard's command. Microfilm Reel 94-2007-2.] (Box 7)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department Abstracts of Orders, Letters, etc., sent out [Little Rock, Ark.?] 12 June -19 Sept. 1862, ms.d., 103 p., 3 p.; [Abstract of military records in General Hindman's command. Microfilm Reel 91-2089.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department Abstracts of Military Papers Fort Smith, Ark., etc. 31 Oct. 1862 -8 Jan. 1863, ms.d., 123 double spread pages; [Abstract of papers received in the A. A. Gen's Office in General Hindman's command; withreference to endorsements in Register A. Microfilm Reel 91-2089.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Copybook of General Orders. Little Rock, Ark., etc. 31 May -30 Dec. 1862., ms.d., 65 p.; printed orders inserted.; [Copybook of General Orders from General Hindman's command. Microfilm Reel 91-2089.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Copybook of Special Orders. Little Rock, Ark., etc. 1 June -18 Dec. 1862., ms.d., 38, 80 p.; [Copybook of Special Orders from General Hindman's command. Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Copybook of Special Orders. Little Rock, Ark. 11 June -19 Aug. 1862., ms.d., 147 p.; [Copybook of Special Orders from General Hindman's and Holmes's command. Printedorders inserted. Microfilm Reel 91-2089.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Register of Orders, Letters, and Abstracts. Little Rock, Ark. 19 Sept. 1862 -3 March. 1863., ms.d., 29, 63, 46, 2 p.; [Register of orders, letters, abstracts receipts of orders, and an outline of Organizationof the First Corps of the Trans-Mississippi Army in General Hindman's command. Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Register of Endorsements. Fort Smith, Ark. 5 Nov. 1862 -8 Jan. 1863., ms.d., 74 p. double spread pages.; [Register of endorsements sent from the A.A. General's Office, in General Hindman'scommand. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Register of Endorsements. [Little Rock, Ark.] 5 Jan. -19 Feb. 1863., ms.d., 71 p. double spread pages.; [Register of endorsements sent from the A.A. General's Office, in General Hindman'scommand. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 8)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Copybook of Letters. Little Rock, Ark. 1 June -12 Dec. 1862., ms.vol., 420 p.; [From General Hindman's command, et al. Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 9)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Copybook of Letters and Orders. Clarkesville, Ark. 2 Jan. -14 March 1863., ms.vol., 148 p.; [From General Hindman's command, et al. Microfilm Reel 90-2021.] (Box 9)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Copybook of Orders and Letters. Little Rock, Ark. 11 June -30 Dec. 1862., ms.vol., 201 p.; [From General Hindman's command, et al. A 20 page description of the Cane Hill and PrairieGrove campaigns are at the end of the volume. Microfilm Reel 90-2021.] (Box 9)
    - Confederate States of America. Army. Trans-Mississippi Department. Copybook of Telegrams. Little Rock, Ark. 2 June -9 Oct. 1862., ms.vol., 321 p. (4 p. insert); [Copybook of telegraphic dispatches Memphis and Little Rock Line, from General Hindman, etal. Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 9)
    - Alexander, Peter Wellington Notes on civil engineering from lectures at Franklin College. Athens, GA 13 May 1844., a.ms., 108 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 4)
    - Alexander, Peter Wellington Letterbook. Macon, GA 20 Oct. -11 Nov. [1865?], a.vol., 24 p., 1 p.; [Editorial letters on Reconstruction. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 4)
    - Alexander, Peter Wellington Letterbook. Atlanta, GA 15 Feb. -22 Nov. 1875., a.vol., 184 a.l.s., 236 p. (copies).; [Onionskin copybook. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 4)
    - Alexander, Peter Wellington Letterbook. Atlanta and Marietta, GA 4 Dec. 1875 -14 Nov. 1879., a.vol., 499 p.; [Letterpress book of P. W. Alexander's law office. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 4)
    - Smith & Alexander. Account book. Columbus, GA 28 Aug. 1869 -1 March 1887., a.vol., 2, 45 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 18)
    - Smith & Alexander Letterbook. Columbus, GA 20 Aug. 1867 -31 Oct. 1868., a.vol., 473 p.; [Letterpress book of the law office of Jamse Milton Smith (1823-1890) and P. W. Alexander. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 18)
    - Smith & Alexander Letterbook. Columbus and Atlanta GA 6 Feb. 1871 -1 Dec. 1872., a.vol., 480 p.; [Letterpress book. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 18)
    - Ferrat, John B. Letterbook. Norfolk and Richmond, VA 9 May 1862 -1 July 1863., a.vol., 39 p.; ["Captured from the Yankees at the Battle of Sharpsburg, MD Sept. 17th 1862." Not on Microfilm.] (Box 12)
    - Shorter, Theresa Scrapbook. Columbus, GA March 1859., 39 p. of illus, 1 ms. poem.; [1, 5, 55 p. of newspapers clippings. "Captured from the Yankees at the Battle of Sharpsburg, MD Sept. 17th 1862." Not on Microfilm.] (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Documents
  - "Cavalry tactics: single rank formation." [n.p.] [n.d.], 27 p.; [Draft for the printer. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Charges against various officers and enlisted men. [n.p.] [n.d.], 15 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Court-martial proceedings. Camp Rector 15 Aug. 1862., 27 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Court-martial papers. [n.p.] 1862., 14 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Indian affairs (letters, reports). [n.p.] [n.d.], 16 p.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Leave of absence requests and grants. [n.p.] 1862., 6 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Resignations. [n.p.] 1862., 19 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Transfer of change of service requests. [n.p.] 1862., 5 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Various documents: contracts, medical reports, etc. [n.p.] 1862., 20 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Orders
  - General Holmes General Orders. [n.p.] 1862., 7 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 14)
  - General Orders from various Generals. [n.p.] 1862 -1864., 15 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - General Hindman Miscellaneous Orders and Circulars. Subsistence, receipts, etc. [n.p.] 1861 -1863., 27 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Orders and Circulars. Subsistence, receipts, etc. from various Generals. [n.p.] 1861 -1863., [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Special Orders from various Generals. [n.p.] 1862., 12 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 14)
  - General Hindman Special Orders. [n.p.] [n.d.], 11 p.; [Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 14)
  - General Hindman Special Orders. [n.p.] Jan. 1863., 28 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 14)
  - Special Orders from various Generals. [n.p.] Aug. 19, 1863 -Dec. 13, 1864., 5 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - General Johnston Special Orders. [n.p.] Jan. & Feb. 1864., 38 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - General Johnston Special Orders. [n.p.] March1864., 42 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - General Johnston Special Orders. [n.p.] April -Nov. 1864., 39 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 14)
  - Reports
  - Field Reports. [n.p.] 27 Nov. 1862 -31 July 1864., 8 pieces.; [From Generals Anderson, Brown, Clayton, Cooper, and Hallonquist. Not on Microfilm.] (Box 17)
  - General Hindman Field Report. [n.p.] 22 Jan. 1863 -29 April 1864., 10 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 17)
  - General Hood Field Reports. [n.p.] 1 March 1862 -10 July 1864., 11 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 17)
  - General Stevenson Field Reports. [n.p.] 23 May -21 July 1864., 10 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 17)
  - General Stewart Field Reports. [n.p.] 9 March -27 June 1864., 10 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 17)
  - General Parsons Reports - deserters. [n.p.] 21 Feb. 1863., 6 pieces.; [Microfilm ] (Box 17)
  - Reports - deserters (from various officers). [n.p.] 5 Nov. 1862 -28 Feb. 1863, 15 pieces.; [Microfilm] (Box 17)
  - Reports - medical. [n.p.] 27 June 1862 -24 April 1864., 21 pieces.; [Microfilm.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - prisoners. [n.p.] 20 June 1862 -18 Sept. 1863, 19 pieces.; [Microfilm.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - supplies. [n.p.] 14 Nov. 1861 -8 Aug. 1863., 18 pieces.; [Microfilm.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - transportation. [n.p.] 28 Feb. 1862 -31 Jan. 1864., 9 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 91-1090.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - transportation. [n.p.] 28 Feb. 1862., 17 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 91-1090.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - troops. [n.p.] 12 April -19 Oct. 1862., 17 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - troops. [n.p.] 27 Aug. -3 Sept. 1862., 6 pieces.; [With accompanying report. Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - troops. [n.p.] 24 -30 Oct. 1862., 5 pieces.; [With accompanying report. Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - troops. [n.p.] 20 Oct. -28 Dec. 1862, 17 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 17)
  - Reports - troops. [n.p.] 28 June -31 July 1862 and [n.d.], 11 pieces.; [Microfilm Reel 11566.] (Box 17)
- Southern United States Newspapers
  - Advertiser and Register. Issues. Mobile, Ala., 7 June 1863, 167 whole issues, front issues and second copies.; [Not on Microfilm Also known as Mobile Daily Advertiser and Register.] (Box 3-14)
  - Mobile Daily Advertiser and Register. Issues. Mobile, Ala., 1 July 1863 -1 June 1864, 109 front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Mobile Register and Advertiser. Issues. Mobile, Ala., 1 Aug. 1862 -31 May 1863, 9 whole issues and front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - The Army Argus and Crisis. Issues. Mobile, Ala., 1 July -27 Aug. 1864, 8 whole and incomplete issues.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Daily Dispatch. Issues. Richmond, VA, 14 Nov. 1861 -11 Feb. 1864., 27 whole issues and front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Daily Morning News. Issues. Savannah, GA, 15 Oct. 1862 -31 May 1864., 18 front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Georgia Messinger. Issues. Macon, GA, 5 March 1835 -11 July 1865., 107 whole issues and duplicates.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Mobile Daily Tribune. Issues. Mobile, Ala., 31 May 1863 -11 July 1865., 17 whole issues and front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Mobile Evening News. Issues Mobile, Ala., 2 Oct. 1862 -15 March 1865., 33 front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Mobile Evening Telegraph. Issues. Mobile, Ala., 19 June 1863 -6 March 1865., 8 front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - The Savannah Republican. Issues. Savannah, Ga., 8 July 1861 -21 Nov. 1864., 723 whole issues, front pages, and second copies.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Southern Confederacy. Issues. Atlanta, Ga. 6 March 1861 -25 Sept. 1862., 46 whole issues and front pages.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Newspapers (various). [n.p.] 20 June 1840 -1 Oct. 1864., 1 folder, 14 pieces.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 3-14)
  - Newspaper clippings from southern newspapers about the Civil War: various battles and campaigns, speeches and proclamations, war casualties, etc. [n.p.] [n.d.]., 1 box, ca. 700 items.; [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 15)
- Addition (1976)
  - Family correspondence Miscellaneous manuscripts Miscellaneous financial and legan documents. [n.p.] [n.d.]., [Shelved after newspapers. ] (Box 11)
  - Confederate States of America. Trans-Mississippi Department. Papers from the command of General T. C. Hindman. [n.p.] [n.d.]., [Microfilm Reel 91-2090.] (Box 10)
  - Photographs Printed Material Index to the "Selected Cataloged Correspondence" microfilm by Michael E. Banasik. [n.p.] [n.d.], [Not on Microfilm.] (Box 10)